Guide to the Julian Shakespeare Carr Papers, 1880-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Julian Shakespeare Carr papers 1880-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Carr, Julian Shakespeare.
0.5 linear feet Extent: approx. 85 items
Julian Carr was a tobacco and textile manufacturer and civic leader of Durham (Durham Co.), N.C. He also served on the Board of Trustees of Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.). The collection includes material related to Carr's service on the Board of Trustees as well as personal family papers. The material ranges in date from 1880-1982.
RL.01440
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Julian Shakespeare Carr Papers were received in 1941 and 1978.
Biographical Note
Julian Shakespeare Carr was born October 12, 1845 to John W. Carr and Eliza P. Carr in North Carolina. He attended the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and served in the Confederate Army. After the war, Carr became a partner of W. T. Blackwell and Co., a tobacco manufacturing firm in Durham. His donation of land to Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.), along with the financial support of Washington Duke, allowed the struggling school the opportunity to move to Durham. Carr served on the Board of Trustees of the College, prior to and after its move to Durham. In 1924, the school would be renamed Duke University. Carr died on April 29, 1924 and is buried in Durham's Maplewood Cemetery.
Collection Overview
The collection includes about 72 items which cover the period when Carr served as Treasurer of the Board of Trustees of Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) and on the Committee of Management with John Wesley Alspaugh and James Alexander Gray. The bulk of this correspondence deals with attempts by Carr, largely unsuccessful, to call in notes pledged to the endowment of the College. There are significant letters from Alspaugh, Gray, and John Franklin Crowell, as well as a Treasurer's Report (circa 1885), other financial matters, and lists of Methodist Church assessments made to support Trinity College. Other subjects treated include the settlement of an estate, bills for the widow of Braxton Craven, and a student petition for the replacement of Professor W. T. Gannaway. There are also letters from John W. Sanborn, a candidate for the College's presidency. The other items in the collection include clippings and a photograph pertaining to the Carr family and homes; a farm journal (1910-1911) with instructions from Carr to his manager, B. S. Skinner, and samples of chewing and twist tobacco and handmade cigarettes produced in the 1880s at W. T. Blackwell's Durham tobacco company.
Subject Headings
Carr, Julian Shakespeare; Alspaugh, John W., 1831-1912; Gray, James Alexander; Crowell, J. F. (John Franklin), 1857-1931; Skinner, B. S.; Sanborn, John W.; Carr family; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.). Board of Trustees; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.)--Finance; W. T. Blackwell and Company (Durham, N.C.); Farm management -- North Carolina; Tobacco industry -- North Carolina -- Durham; Durham (N.C.)--Economic conditions
Related Material
Julian Shakespeare Carr Papers
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List
  - Information Folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1880, 1884-1885 Sept. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1885 Nov.-1887, 1891 May, undated (Box 1)
  - Financial Papers (including Treasurer's Report), 1884-circa 1885 (Box 1)
  - Methodist Church Assessments, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Democratic Clubs, 1890 (Box 1)
  - Printed Address to the People of Durham County, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Printed Material (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1891-1982 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Carr's Home, "Waverly Honor," 1883 (Box 1)
  - Samples of chewing and twist tobacco, handmade cigarettes, loose smoking tobacco and rolling papers produced in the 1880s at W. T. Blackwell's Durham tobacco company. (Box 2)
  - Image of Carr as an older man, dressed in military uniform (likely Confederate) (Opaperfolder 1)